# Himanshu Jain

Minneapolis, MN (Open to Relocation) | jainmanshu@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/hjain64 | hjain64.github.io

#### **SOFTWARE ENGINEER**

Experienced Software Engineer specializing in building next-generation solutions, optimizing systems, and developing applications for a competitive edge. Committed to delivering exceptional results for customers through technical proficiency and creative problem-solving that cater to the evolving needs of modern businesses.

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Expertise: Javascript ES6 | Typescript | Node.js | Python | HTML5+CSS | React | Redux | REST-API | WebPack
- Proficient: GraphQL | Express.js | Liquibase | Next.js | Angular.js | Django | Jest | Enzyme | D3 | Monorepo | Selenium |
   WebDriverIO | Elasticsearch | FastAPI | Docker | Redis | PostgreSQL | MongoDB | Github Actions
- Familiarity: Kafka | Kubernetes | Apache Spark | RabbitMQ | Jenkins | BuildKite | AWS (EC2, ECS, lambda, S3, SQS) | MySQL | Snowflake | Azure | Spring-Boot | OIDC | OAuth2.0 | Shadcn | Micro-frontends | Web-GL Maps

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Trimble Inc. June 2018 - Present

Trimble Inc. provides technology solutions for the transportation and logistics industry, offering tools for fleet management, routing, and optimization.

# Software Engineer - 3 | Aug 2023 - Present

- Integrated **deep learning models** into the **data pipeline** for predictive analytics, contributing to the development of a recommendation system that boosted **user engagement by 25%**.
- Designed a scalable Kafka-based services for ingesting and processing large-scale GPS Breadcrumbs data feeds, achieving a throughput of 5,000 messages per second with an average end-to-end latency of less than 10 seconds.
- Conducted **code reviews**, authored technical **design documentation**, **mentored** junior team members, and facilitated **agile** practices, resulting in a streamlined development process and heightened team productivity.

# Software Engineer - 2 | Jan 2020 - July 2023

- Deployed Single-Sign-On (SSO) capability through a tailored federation approach connecting **OAuth2.0** with enterprise identity using **openID connect**, successfully **migrating over 100,000 users**, resulting in a **30% reduction in login times**.
- Led the development of an **intelligent route navigation** system seamlessly integrated into an Trimble **GIS** product, optimizing fleet management operations and significantly **reducing fuel consumption by 15%**.
- Achieved **95% code quality coverage** milestone by utilizing **Jest/Enzyme** for the meticulous **unit testing** and **Selenium/WebdriverIO** for the **automation** end-to-end testing framework.
- Owned and developed Node microservices using PostgreSQL as database, Kafka for event streaming, Redis for caching,
   Elasticsearch for document store, Docker/Kubernetes for containerization and AWS for reliability and scalability.

## Software Engineer - 1 | Jun 2018 - Dec 2019

- Implemented SaaS-based NextGen fleet telematics application, optimizing fleet management for a substantial customer base, achieving 35% increase in customer retention resulting in additional \$5M in annual revenue growth.
- Built a robust internal open-source web component library, based on React with adherence to Material-UI design
  principles and UX considerations, resulting in an average of 150+ weekly downloads, documented using Storybook.js.

#### **RESEARCH AND INTERNSHIP**

# **Titus Lab - University of Minnesota** | *Undergrad Research Assistant*

Jan 2018 - May 2018

- Developed and documented a cellular image analysis application responsible for extracting key parameters (cell count, area, intensity, filopodia length) for Metazoa and Amoebozoa, vital for early-stage cancer cell detection.
- Refactored the application code from MatLab to an automated ImageJ JavaScript application, cutting down the overall stats generation time by 80%, significantly improving performance and elevating user experience.

## **ConvergeOne** | Voice Solution Engineer Intern

May 2017 - Aug 2017

- Engineered a contact center application with Cisco Unified Communications Manager, adhering closely to agile methodologies, resulting in a significant **66% reduction** in average **call wait time** from 15 minutes to 5 minutes.
- Orchestrated full-stack application development, showcasing proficiency in backend technologies such as **C#**, .NET, SQL, REST API, VXML, and frontend technologies including **Typescript**, **Angular.js**, Karma testing, and Bower.

## **EDUCATION**